こんにちは、みなさん。 BioC Asia 2021を楽しんでいらっしゃることと思います。
本日は、カンファレンスの主催者に講演招待をいただきありがとうございます。
これはライブトークではありませんが私の初めてのキーノートトークでありとてもわくわくしています。今日の私のトークはBioconductorについてです。
Bioconductorとは何か、そしてそのコアチームがBioconductorというプロジェクトをどのように支援しているかを紹介します。
私が一般的なRおよびコンピューティングの会議に参加し始めたときに最初に驚いたのは、Bioconductorが単一のRパッケージであるという誤解でした。
Bioconductorプロジェクトは、単一のパッケージではなく、それよりはるかに大きいものです。
Bioconductorは、オープンソースおよびオープン開発のRパッケージリポジトリシステムです。
それは遺伝学およびゲノミクスデータの分析、理解、および視覚化を中心に扱っています。
Bioconductorには現在2000を超えるパッケージがあります。
加えて専門的な実験やアノテーションのデータやワークフローもあります。それらはBioconductorのインターフェースを通じて利用できます。
ただし、Bioconductorは単なるパッケージリポジトリシステムではありません。
それは真に巧妙に築き上げられた組織です。多くの人が関わりプロジェクトの方向性を決めています。
現在、「科学」「技術」「コミュニティ」の3つの主要な諮問委員会があります。
科学諮問委員会は招待されたメンバーのみの委員会です。
それはプロジェクトの科学的方向性に関する外部の助言と監視を提供します。
一方コミュニティ諮問委員会は毎年春に委員会に加わるためのオープンな公開投票によって選出されます。
技術諮問委員会はプロジェクトおよびパッケージレベルのインフラストラクチャについてアドバイスします。
一方、コミュニティ諮問委員会はBioconductorコミュニティの発展、強化、および多様化に取り組んでいます。
誰でもこれらの2つの委員会のポジションに立候補することができます。
技術委員会の場合は、Bioconductorとプログラミングの知識や
専門的な科学技術の背景があると便利かもしれません
コミュニティ委員会は特に、人種、民族、教育レベルそしてBioconductorの経験の組み合わせを目指して、可能な限り多様化を図りたいと考えています。
興味がある場合は、
春先にBioconductorのサポートサイトとコミュニティSlackチャンネルで志願の募集を探してください。
Bioconductorは単なる単一のパッケージではなくそれ以上のものであるという話に戻りましょう。
Bioconductorはパッケージリポジトリであり組織でもありますが、さらに重要なのは、おそらく最も重要なことですが
コミュニティであるということです。そのためBioconductorは次の目的のためにリソースやインフラを提供しようとがんばっています。
それは経験豊富なパッケージメンテナ、開発者、およびユーザーを、
経験の浅い人々とリンクさせ、この協力的で歓迎的なコミュニティを育成するためです。
ではBioconductorユーザーはどのように、どこでコミュニティとつながるのでしょうか?
それにはいくつかの異なる場所があります。注目すべきはBioconductorのサポートサイトとコミュニティSlackチャンネルそして
数多く存在するカンファレンスワークショップとトレーニングイベントです。ワークショップとイベントは年を通じて起こっています。
また新しく展開されたメンターシッププログラムもあります。私は今あなたにそれらそれぞれを簡単に說明できます。
Bioconductorのサポートサイトは多くのユーザーが行く最初の場所です。
そこではBioconductorパッケージを用いた解析やトラブルシュートの質問をし、アドバイスをもらいます。
このサポートサイトはBioconductorパッケージの質問に特化しています。そしてBioconductorにパッケージを提出したすべてのメンテナーは
サポートサイトにサインアップする必要があります。もしメンテナーのパッケージ名でタグ付けされた質問が来たら
メンテナーにはその通知が来るようになっています。サポートサイトには何千人ものユーザーがいます。
サポートサイトはコミュニティの知識と経験を活用するための優れたリソースになりえます。パッケージのタグをクリックすると検索ができます。
またはタグのタブに移動してパッケージを検索することもできます。そして既存の投稿や質問を見ることができます。
もしあなたが必要とするものに関係のある何かが見つからなければ
あなたは新しい質問を投稿できます。ask a questionタブをクリックすることでそれができます。
有益なタイトルと質問に関連するパッケージのタグを投稿に付けるようにしてください。
本文には Markdown もしくはプレーンテキストまたはHTMLを使用します。もし問題、コード実行のエラーがある場合
できるだけ多くのコード例をコードセクションに含めてください。また必ずプラットフォームの情報、
RとBioconductorのバージョンも含めてください。すると我々が回答を適切に調整できるので。
Bioconductorチームはニュース機能を使って重要なアナウンスを投稿します。
それはリリース、パッケージ、カンファレンス、選挙、およびその他のニュースイベントのためのものです。
BioconductorコミュニティのSlackチャンネルもあります。私はみなさんにそのチャンネルに参加することをおすすめします。
そこには多くの特定の議論に役立つチャンネルがあります。
例えばマイクロバイオーム、メタボロミクス、プロテオミクスといったようなチャンネルがあります。
後で説明するコアインフラストラクチャの部分について質問するチャネルもありますが、
ビルドシステムの質問用のbioc-buildsや、
experimenthub、annotationhub、またはbiocfilecacheの質問用のbiochubsなどのチャネルもあります。
年間を通じて多くのカンファレンス、ワークショップ、トレーニングイベントがあります。
メインのウェブサイトにはBioconductorイベントカレンダーがあり、誰でもBioconductor関連のイベントを送信して宣伝できます。
events@bioconductor.org に電子メールを送信するか
まもなく利用可能になるフォーム版で、誰でもウェブページに含めるイベントを送信できます。
イベントの最小要件はBioconductorとの関連性、およびBioconductor行動規範を守ることです。
カンファレンスは常に楽しい時であり、コミュニティやネットワークの他のメンバーと会うための素晴らしい方法です。
毎年恒例のイベントとなっている、このBioCAsiaを楽しんでいただければ幸いです。
また、夏の終わりに米国で通常開催されるメインのBioCカンファレンスと、
毎年恒例のEuroBioCカンファレンスがあり、現在予定されている次のカンファレンスは2022年3月です。
近年、他の国でもBioconductorのイニシアチブが見られることに興奮しています。
Bioconductorはその代表者をバイオインフォマティクスソフトウェア開発者のコミュニティの一部に喜んで送っています。
具体的には毎年1週間にわたるメキシコとラテンアメリカの
スペイン語でのカンファレンスやワークショップ(訳注: CDSB)ですとか
ワークショップやウェビナーのシリーズとして立ち上げられたH3ABioNetそしてH3Africaに代表者を送っています。
(訳注: 後者は)アフリカの人がコーディングや研究を促進するのを助けるものです。
これらはBioconductorが加わっている多くのワークショップやウェビナーそしてトレーニングの機会のほんの一部です。
それらは年間を通じて世界中で立ち上げられており、
Bioconductorコミュニティが成長し、私たちがワールドワイドな研究の一部になれていることに本当に興奮しています。
ところでそれらはコミュニティとつながるすばらしいリソースですが、
ちょっと前の組織のスライドに戻りたいと思います。なぜなら私たちはその最後のエントリーであるコアチームをスキップしたので。
コアチームは、プロジェクトの機能において重要な役割を果たします。
それは小さな特化された開発者のグループで、コアパッケージとプロジェクトレベルのインフラストラクチャの開発、保守、強化を支援します。
それが本当に意味していることはどのようなことでしょうか? ほとんどの人は次のように考えていると思います。
「コアチームはコアパッケージとパッケージメンテナンスだけ管理している」と。しかし実際には我々は
それよりもっと多くのことを行っています。私たちはBioconductorがプロジェクトであることについて話しました。そこには多くのインフラストラクチャの要素があります。
それらはプロジェクトを機能させるためにあります。それではそのリソースについて考えてみましょう。
私たちは今しがたコアインフラストラクチャがコアチームが保守しているものに含まれることを見直しました。
そんなわけでまずコアチームが更新と維持を行う責任があるものとしてメインのウェブサイト bioconductor.org があります。
ウェブサイトは完全にコードベースで
約20分毎に再生成され、常に最新の情報が確認できるようになっています。
同様にサポートサイトのウェブサイトもコードベースです。ありがたいことに私たちは
サポートサイトのモデルとしたBiostars、特にNatay Aberraからのサポートと助けを得ています。
ですがサポートサイトの維持とメンテナンスにはコアチームが関与しています。
またコミュニティSlackチャンネルに現れる質問を監視・解決してもいます。
多くの場合に問題、コメント、懸念のフォローアップや調査につながっています。
また、多くのコアチームメンバーがカンファレンスやワークショップの資料のプレゼンに参加しています。
普通のカンファレンスのコンポーネントに関与している場合もあります。例えばワークショップをホストするための専用のウェブページシステムですとか
参加者のためのコンピューター環境を用意するなどです。そんな具合にもコアチームは
管理や促進を助けています。そんなわけでみなさんはもうバックエンドのインフラストラクチャの重要性をお分かりになられたかと思います。
続いて、ユーザーと開発者の2つの視点からBioconductorについて考えていきたいと思います。
and along the way we'll discuss additional
important project infrastructure that the
core team helps develop maintain and enhance to
try to provide a good experience to the community
so thinking about a user how does a user
interact with bioconductor traditionally
i think most users were using our terminal
or rstudio which is still highly popular and
widely utilized but there are also newer available
technologies and projects like using docker images
or cloud-based initiatives like the anvil
project that allow a different user experience
for our terminal and rstudio users there's a
cram package bioc manager that is downloaded
installed from cran and provides access to all
packages in bioconductor and crayon repositories
the anvil which stands for analysis visualization
and informative lab space is an nhgri project
it provides a secure cloud-based computing
environment for analysis i will not go into
detail here about anvil and docker images but i
encourage everyone to attend natashas talk where
i believe some of these concepts and resources
will be covered i will mention that the anvil
bioconductor package provides a different
install function designed specifically for
use with the bioconductor docker images and the
anvil computing space that can provide fast binary
package installation why is this significant well
some packages require compilation which can take
several seconds package binaries are pre-compiled
allowing for a near instantaneous installation the
limitation of binaries is that package binaries
are specific to the system configuration to which
they were generated which is why they're
only available for use with the docker
another important concept for users especially
new users is how to find packages of interest
in bios manager there's a function available
that shows a listing of all available packages
or you could use a search term to find packages
but that assumes some a priori knowledge the
bioc views page and package landing pages
can be really useful for finding packages
off the bioconductor.org home page there's
a link to available software packages
this takes you to what we call our bioseed views
page and includes software annotation experiment
and workflow packages books are coming soon
you can either search for terms of interest
like single cell or proteomics to get a list
of packages or if you know a package name
you can search for it specifically like
genomic ranges or summarized experiment
the rank ordering is in order of most downloaded
to lease downloaded and if you click on a package
name it takes you to a bioconductor's package
landing page the page has badges to indicate
package health and information on the package
like the description documentation what package
dependencies or reverse dependencies there are
and in the bottom a link to download the package
directly instead of through bioc manager access to
the code base in git.bioconductor.org and package
download statistics probably the most helpful on
this page is the package documentation that a user
can browse through before downloading a package to
see if it's appropriate for their type of analysis
so before switching to a developer's
point of view let's revisit the core team
and in these few concepts for users what sort
of infrastructure is required in the background
so there's obviously some package maintenance
with regard to bioc manager anvil anvil specific
packages and bioseat views packages there's a
concept of a daily build of all bioconductor
packages so that they're available through the
bioc manager install function there's generation
and upkeep of docker images so bioconductor docker
images for both release and develop branches
and an anvil specific docker image that
needs to be submitted to the anvil platform
there's also the binary package generation
for those provide packages provided through
anvil install and then there's the website
code and website interaction so that you
could see that biosea views page and package
landing pages and the constant regeneration
of the website to make sure that all that
information stays up to date to the latest
and then at the bottom of the packing landing
pages i mentioned it briefly but there's package
download statistics that get calculated for each
package as well so again hopefully that you can
see while it may seem like trivial and basic
functionality that there's a lot that needs to
be in place behind the scenes for everything
to function properly and interact properly
so the core team has a subset of packages
that are considered core packages and core
team maintained but most of the packages
in bioconductor are community contributed
anyone from the community is welcome to
develop and submit a package to bioconductor
there are certain specific package requirements
that should be implemented when developing
and a package will undergo a review
process once a package is accepted
then it's added to the daily builder and
available through bioc manager install
so package specific requirements can be
found at contributions.bioconnector.org
and the developer section of the main website
we are in the process of moving information
from the developer section of the website to
the contributions.bioconductor.org location
so eventually all the information
will be in one location
but let's go over some of the key concepts that
should be implemented when developing a package
one of the main things is reusing or extending
existing classes and using the well-developed
import and export methods for certain data types
bioconductor has the concept of interoperability
so if a user wants to use one package to import a
different normalize and a third to visualize the
manipulation of data from one package to the next
should be minimal if not eliminated completely for
the user so ideally the output of one should
be the input to another this is why we like to
emphasize using or extending any of the existing
class structures another good practice worth
mentioning is the caching of web-based data when
possible this way if a user is without internet or
requests the same file from a website or a website
is temporary unavailable they don't have to
re-download and could potentially use a previously
downloaded version instead of having to wait for
the internet or re-download data another good
practice is implementing unit tests it's strongly
recommended while tests can seem burdensome
if added to the development process early it
can actually aid in development so testing for
things like edge cases and having both positive
and negative tests can ensure proper proper
functionality biggest thing that bioconductor
is also going to insist upon is a really
detailed vignette with runnable code examples
so vignettes are compiled when built so it can
also help ensure proper functioning code but we
like detailed vignettes because ideally this gives
your users an understanding of the package and
the unique functionality that the package provides
and these are just a few concepts of the many that
you'll find on this contributions.bioconductor.org
page so once a package is developed a user then
submits to the bioconductor new submission tracker
on github there's some useful information on the
home page about what to expect and how
to submit related or dependent packages
but to submit a new issue you go to open a new
issue under bioconductor contributions the title
should be your package name all packages currently
require a github repository location and the link
should be updated pointing to this location a
package then is an awaiting moderation stage
a reviewer will be assigned and the package
added to our get.bioconductor.org location
and a build triggered on all three major os
platforms linux mac and windows once a package
is building and checking without error the
reviewer will do an in-depth review of the package
and offer comments suggestions or request changes
consistent with bioconductor package requirements
there's an open dialogue in the review process
open to the community and governed by the
bioconductor code of conduct once a package is
accepted it's added to the nightly daily builder
bioconductor uses get for version control of
package source code bioconductor builds only from
get.bioconductor.org and users must push
changes to this location to propagate
them to users from a few times a week to daily
the bioconductor builders will do a get clone
a version of the package and then do an r
command install r command build and r command
check if the package installs builds and checks
cleanly and has a valid version bump for changes
the package is propagated and becomes available
through the bioc manager install function
maintainers can find the build reports from
the main website in the lower right corner
marked build reports this page indicates
how frequently the builds take place
if we click on browse for any of the build reports
you'll get a list of every bioconductor package
and the status through each stage the top of
the page has a time stamp to indicate when it
was generated and each package has information
on the version git commit and get date that the
builder used for that report you can click on any
stage indicator for more information and results
so what infrastructure is needed for
everything just discussed for submitting
a package well there's evaluating and
updating of the package guidelines
there's the code that interacts with
the package submission process on github
and code specific to the new submission
process on each of the three develop builders
the core team also participates currently
in package reviews for new submissions
there is facilitating the entire
bioconductor get ecosystem
which includes the get.bioconductor.org
main repository location for all of the
bioconductor packages a git contributions
app that manages ssh credentials of users
get a light application that manages which users
have access to which packages and gut hooks that
respond to different triggering events there's
also the bioconductor build system called the bbs
which is a large undertaking of the core team
there are minimally six build machines that
require system administration and the underlying
code base on each to handle the get clone the r
command install the r command build the r command
check the package propagation and the generation
of the build reports and there's minimally six
builders because for both the bioconductor release
and bioconductor devel branches we cover the
three main os platforms of mac linux and windows
so briefly i wanted to also touch upon why
bioconductor has a release in a devel branch
bioconductor is closely associated with r most
years in spring r has a release bioconductor
then needs to update which version of
r is being used for packages to insured
continued proper functionality bioconductor
has two releases of gear a spring and a fall
where the devel branch is released and becomes the
new release from roughly late april and early may
when the new version of r is released both the
bioconductor release and devel branch use that
stapled release version of r or our patched
version in fall normally late october early
november bioconductor does a second release
at this time the bioconductor release branch
still uses that stable rr patch version but the
devel bioconductor branch switches to use r devel
in preparation for the next r release in spring
having a devel branch allows maintainers to
adapt to changes in base r as well as changes in
any other dependent packages that they may have
and then have minimal disruption or
downtime to the end user bioconductor
encourage package maintainers to enhance and
make major changes on the development branch
and restrict changes on the release branch
to minor bug corrections again also reasoning
that there would be a place for development and
potential breakage without affecting the end users
the core team is always extremely busy during
release time and with release related tasks it
involves updating versions of r and bioconductor
on minimumly the six builders emailing maintainers
that ignored the build failure notifications to
try and fix their packages to avoid deprecation
and removal from bioconductor reviewing the
influx of newly submitted packages for inclusion
fixing or modifying any core packages that
require such attention adding release related
annotation resources creating new branches on
get.bioconductor.org for all the packages for
the new release and collating all the news files
from packages to generate the release announcement
there is another key infrastructure piece that
the core team maintains that has gained increasing
popularity in recent years the concept of the
bioconductor hubs annotation hub and experiment
hub as a brief background git does not allow large
files and our current git system does not support
get lfs which means there has to be an alternative
way to provide large data sets to users
bioconductor insists data to be hosted on a
secure public or institutional server like
zenodo amazon s3 buckets microsoft azure among
other trusted sites or direct access to web
resources or databases if available like ensemble
or ncbi rather than privately hosting data on say
a github or dropbox if you're developing a
package we encourage a discussion about data
hosting on other platforms on the bioslee dash
devel r-projects.org developers mailing list
if a maintainer does not have access to
such a resource bioconductor provides
an amazon s3 bucket for use we are however
actively investigating a migration of location
from amazon s3 to microsoft azure developers can
download resources directly from the trusted sites
but must implement a caching mechanism in
the background and we highly recommend the
bioconductor core package bioc file cache the
other alternative to downloading directly and
implementing bios you file cache is to list the
data in the annotation hub or experiment hub
the annotation hub and the experiment hub are
databases with references to the external data
for download the hub interfaces provide a querying
mechanism on metadata provided at inclusion of the
data into the database when using the hub
interface for download it already uses bioc
file cache as a caching mechanism so a maintainer
does not have to implement it themselves the other
advantage to listing the data in the hubs is the
findability of resources outside of r or outside
the use of the associated bioconductor package
there are bioconductor core packages experiment
hub and annotation hub that can be queried for
data of different types or from different sources
the resources can be searched either through a
query performed within r or investigation through
the hub apis and annotationhub.bioconductor.org
or experimenthub.bioconductor
the api is admittedly a little crude and
we are working on a revamp there's also a
shiny version to query hub resources that has
been developed and should be announced soon
the query function in r will take a list of terms
and return resources matching search criteria
for example you can see we queried
here for ensembl gtf release 103
and homo sapiens which returned four results a
single bracket using the ahid of interest will
give more information on the resource and a double
bracket will download and cache the resource
the requirement to add data to the hubs
is a package that is already or will be
submitted to bioconductor that includes an
inst metadata.csv file with metadata for the
resources that will be added to the database and
an in-script directory with files that indicate
how the data was generated and relevant source
information the vignette creating a hub package
experiment hub or annotation hub in the core
package hub pub describes this in more detail
other questions can be directed to
the hubs at bioconductor.org email
the hubs currently involve a lot of interaction
from the core team we are working on making
enhancements and restructure to try to make it
simpler and easier to submit and maintain hub data
with limited core team interaction currently when
data is submitted to the hubs a core team member
will evaluate the data and metadata provided
if needed assist with uploading data to the
bioconductor provided location again currently
that's an amazon s3 bucket but that could change
and update the database for the metadata
provided so the metadata is available
through the query functions additionally
core team maintenance of the hubs includes
managing server code on the amazon web service ec2
instances that hosts the website and api endpoints
for both hubs and general core package maintenance
of the relevant core packages experiment hub
annotation hub bioc file cache experiment
hub data annotation hub data and hubpub
so there are still other core related
tasks and infrastructure that we just
haven't had time to touch on things like the
amazon web service resources that we utilize
and the microsoft azure project resources
but hopefully this gave everyone an idea
of how much the core team supports in addition to
just general core package health and development
so with that i would like to thank the conference
organizers for inviting me to speak it really
has been an honor and thank you to my fellow core
team members i appreciate all the work and effort
we all put into keeping the project moving
forward and most of all a thank you to the
bioconductor community bioconductor would not be
successful without the contributions of all of you
and whether you're a first time user or a
long-time contributor we really hope that you
found a welcoming and helpful community so please
feel free to send me any questions to my email
or on the community slack if anyone has any
questions about this presentation thank you cheers
you